Finding Aid for Julia Bird Martin papers, 1796-1965
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Julia Bird Martin papers 1796-1965
Martin, Julia Bird
1 linear feet (in 2 boxes) and 1 oversize folder
851848 Aa 2; Ac; UAx
The Slatford Bird families were residents of Ann Arbor, Michigan. Correspondence and family papers, including letters, 1851-1853, of John Slatford written from the California gold fields describing his activities.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Earl W. Martin (donor no. 4699 ) in 1968.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Job Slatford and wife Hannah came to Ann Arbor in 1832. Job Slatford was a carpenter, but with the discovery of gold in California, he and one of his sons, John, set out for the gold field in 1851. Unfortunately, Job Slatford died on the way.
Another of the eight children born to Job and Hannah Slatford was Jane Slatford Bird (born October 6, 1824; died November 29, 1907). Married to John C. Bird on November 5, 1844, she spent most of her life farming and maintaining a peach and apple orchard.
John Bird was the son of Elijah Bird who was born October 1810 in Morris County, New York. Like Job and Hannah Slatford, Elijah Bird had originally come to Ann Arbor in 1832. He thereafter moved to a farm in Argentine in Genesee County, Michigan, then to Linden in 1866.
The Slatford and Bird family papers were collected by Julia Bird Martin, who was the great grand-daughter of Job Slatford and grand-daughter of Jane Slatford Bird. The collection consists of family correspondence from various members of both the Slatford and Bird families. The collection not only relates to family matters, but also includes letters of John Slatford written from the California gold fields, 1851-1853. In addition there are clippings, photographs, postcards, and family memorabilia.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); California--Gold discoveries.; California--Social life and customs; Washtenaw County (Mich.); Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Martin, Julia Bird.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Martin, Julia Bird.; Martin family.; Slatford, Hannah, 1796 or 7-1872.; Slatford family.
Contributors:
Bird, John Chambres, 1822-1887.; Bird, Judson S., d. 1882.; Bird family.; Slatford, Job, 1795-1851.; Slatford, John, b. 1817.; Slatford family.
Genre Terms:
Daguerreotypes.; Photographs.
- Family papers
  - Correspondence and other family documents
    (see also oversize folder, Ac)
    - Undated (Box 1)
    - Undated fragments (Box 1)
    - 1796-1840 (Box 1)
    - 1841-1860 (Box 1)
    - 1861-1870 (Box 1)
    - 1871-1875 (Box 1)
    - 1876-1880 (Box 1)
    - 1881-1890 (Box 1)
    - 1891-1965 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and papers, 1875-1898 concerning Northern Pacific Railroad Company (Box 2)
  - Clippings concerning the Slatford Bird family of Ann Arbor (Box 2)
  - Clippings: largely newspaper front pages with announcements of assassinations of Lincoln, Garfield, etc. (Box 2)
  - Christmas cards and miscellaneous postcards (Box 2)
  - Miscellanea; include printed material (Box 2)
  - Notes and enlarged copies of selected family letters used by Professor Russell Bidlack in his research (Box 2)
  - Photographs
    - Family portraits (Box 2)
    - daguerreotype of Hannah Slatford